window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Digital_Logic - Number_System — Slot 4 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Number_System — Slot 4",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>The number 1102 in base 3 is equivalent to 123 in which base system? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>8</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43803/isro-2013-13\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>When two BCD numbers \\(0\\times14\\) and \\(0\\times08\\) are added what is the binary representation of the resultant number ? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(0\\times22\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(0\\times1c\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(0\\times16\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>results in overflow</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(0\\times22\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43801/isro-2013-11\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Which logic gate is used to detect overflow in 2's compliment arithmetic? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>OR gate</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>AND gate</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>NAND gate</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>XOR gate</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>XOR gate</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/43765/isro-2013-8\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The smallest integer that can be represented by an 8-bit number in 2's complement form is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>-256</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>-128</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>-127</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>-128</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1413/gate2013-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The decimal value 0.5 in IEEE single precision floating point representation has <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>fraction bits of 000...000 and exponent value of 0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>fraction bits of 000...000 and exponent value of -1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>fraction bits of 100...000 and exponent value of 0</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>no exact representation</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>fraction bits of 000...000 and exponent value of -1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39/gate2012-7#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>What is the decimal value of the floating-point number C1D00000 (hexadecimal notation)? (Assume 32-bit, single precision floating point IEEE representation) <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>28</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>-15</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>-26</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>-28</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>-26</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52248/isro2011-8\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>P is a 16-bit signed integer. The 2's complement representation of P is \\((F87B)_{16}\\).\nThe 2's complement representation of 8*P is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((C3D8)_{16}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((187B)_{16}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((F878)_{16}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((987B)_{16}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((C3D8)_{16}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2179/gate2010-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>The addition of 4-bit, two's complement, binary numbers 1101 and 0100 results in <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0001 and an overflow</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1001 and no overflow</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0001 and no overflow</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1001 and an overflow</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>0001 and no overflow</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3546/gate2006-it-7-isro2009-41\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>The two numbers given below are multiplied using the Booth's algorithm <br>\nMultiplicand: 0101 1010 1110 1110<br>\nMultiplier: 0111 0111 1011 1101<br>\nHow many additions/subtractions are required for the multiplication of the above two numbers? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>8</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>12</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>8</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/48065/isro2009-40-gate2008-it_42\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The range of integers that can be represented by an n bit 2's complement number system is: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(-2^{n-1} \\text{ to } (2^{n-1} -1)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(-(2^{n-1} -1) \\text{ to } (2^{n-1} -1)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(-2^{n-1} \\text{ to } 2^{n-1}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(-(2^{n-1} +1) \\text{ to } (2^{n-1} -1)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(-2^{n-1} \\text{ to } (2^{n-1} -1)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1352/gate2005-16-isro2009-18-isro2015-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>\\((1217)_{8}\\) is equivalent to <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((1217)_{16}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((028F)_{16}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((2297)_{10}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((0B17)_{16}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((028F)_{16}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1297/gate2009-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Repeated execution of simple computation may cause compounding of <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>round-off errors</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>syntax errors</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>run-time errors</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>logic errors</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>round-off errors</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50147/isro2008-79\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is termed as minimum error code ? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Binary code</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Gray code</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Excess-3 code</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Octal code</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Gray code</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/17266/isro2008-48\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>A computer uses 8 digit mantissa and 2 digit exponent. If a=0.052 and b=28E+11 then b+a-b will : <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>result in an overflow error</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>result in an underflow error</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>be 0</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>be 5.28E+11</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>be 0</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/45540/isro2008-23\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>If \\((12x)_3 = (123)_x\\), then the value of x is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>3 or 4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of these</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>None of these</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49888/isro2008-20\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
